Just trust your gut. This is
advice whether it's from Oprah or from
Steve Jobs. The broke, the fat, the
lonely, they trust their gut everyday as
they become more and more miserable. But
once you understand these cognitive
biases that I'll cover in this video,
then the world is going to make a whole
bunch more sense to you and you'll be
able to make a whole bunch more money
from it. Now, if you know how to sell,
you will never be broke, but selling is
confusing because buyers are irrational.
However, they are consistent in their
irrationality and once you understand
this, you'll design better offers,
communicate those offers more clearly in
a way that their value can be better
understood, and you can actually save
people from themselves. Now, con men use
these eight biases to separate good
folks from good money, but you will use
these to serve help and impact the
world. I hope at least. And I share
these with you not as a clinician or a
cognitive psychologist, but as a
businessman who has used these eight
biases to make eight figures online
across dozens of different industries.
If you're ready, let's dive in.
Cognitive bias number one, belief
perseverance.
No, it's simple. See, they created this
cover-up to cover-up that cover-up to
cover-up that cover-up to cover-up the
other cover-ups. Here's something
fascinating about the human condition is
the more you convince somebody that they
are wrong, the more they believe they
are right. So, if somebody comes to you
and says, "Man, Jason, I just can't
focus." And you say, "Yeah, you totally
can focus." They're like, "Dude, you
don't understand me. I don't like you.
And because I'm in a state where I'm
unfocused, I will double down on that
state. The fact that you don't
understand me proves that I'm correct."
And so, when we deal with clients on a
persuasive basis, we do not try to
change beliefs. What we do instead is we
make them more uncomfortable
holding on to those beliefs. And I know
that this sounds like slight of hand,
but it isn't. And I'll give you an
example. Clients come to me all the time
saying, "Jason, webinars, I don't think
they work so much anymore." And I say,
"Really? Okay, should I quit doing them
then?" And they're like, "Well, well,
well, hold on a second. Maybe you
shouldn't quit doing them. They just
don't really work for me." How many
times have you tried them? 100, 200, 500
times? You seem pretty confident to
assert to me that they no longer work.
And they're like, "Well, I did it one
time in the last month." And you're
like, "Okay, so help me understand this
so I can be clear here.
You think one attempt in one situation
with one condition means that
it doesn't work? And they're like,
"Well, okay, maybe that's a dumb way of
thinking about it." And this is a
principle I've used over and over again
is if we can change the feeling around
the belief instead of changing the
belief, then the belief will
automatically collapse if it doesn't
serve them. At the same time, we can
easily exaggerate a belief to the point
that it stretches so long that it
breaks. But, I will tell you every day,
99 out of 100 times when I see people
have an interaction, somebody comes and
they say, "This is how I'm feeling." And
the other person tries to convince them,
"No, it's not that bad." Instead, it
would be better to say, "Whoa, that is
terrible. How are you ever going to
survive it?" And then having them try to
defend a belief that doesn't make sense
will allow them to automatically
understand that maybe there's a better
belief that they should be considering
instead. And then when they're in that
position that maybe there is a better
belief, that's when they are now open to
suggestion.
So, what you want to do is you want to
take the beliefs that hold your audience
back, find ways to make it impossible
for those to hold those beliefs and feel
good about them, and then be ready with
the new belief to install in their place
when they turn and ask you, "So, what
should I do?" Don't tell them what to
do. get them to ask you, "What should I
do?" Bias number two, what we call
attentional
bias. Oh, he's so nicely dressed. He
must be trustworthy. So, about a million
years ago in psychology, there was this
concept called seven plus or minus two.
And this was said to be the bits of
information that we can hold in our
heads. And actually, this is not true.
We have it proven that it's even worse
than this. And here's where this came
from. They hired him for a phone company
when they were trying to determine, "How
should we assign telephone numbers?" And
so, the idea was, well, if we have a
number like this, then that's seven
pieces of information. So, just give me
a call on my number. It's 1 2 3 4 5 6 7.
And I'm like, well, that's seven pieces
of information. But that doesn't
actually hold very well because if you
have an area code that you're going to
attach to that, and I know it's a little
bit weirder for those of you that are
not in the United States, but this is
what a number would look like in the US.
It would be area code 5 5 5, and then 1
2 3 4 5 6 7. This is actually nine
pieces of information, but it's chunked
into three groups. And these chunks are
no larger than four pieces per chunk.
And what I've discovered is on any given
topic, you are getting into dangerous
territory if you push the limit of focus
beyond four different pieces. This is
why when I communicate, when I tell,
when I create anything that I want to
have change occur in my audience, I give
them very specific targets early on in
my presentation. I will say, "Today,
we're going to cover these four things.
Success by the end of our presentation
together will look like this in these
three key areas of your life. These are
the four challenges you're going to face
along the way, and here are the three
strategies that we're going to use to
overcome those four challenges.
And when I will teach anything,
especially when I'm selling, I will
typically put it into what I call a road
map. I'll say, "When it comes to this
problem, there are only three things
that really matter at the end of the
day." And then I will try to give them
each one name. So, source, select, sell.
Well, this was a webinar that I did $7
million on when it came to a certain
specific business model. I say, "These
are the three elements of success.
You've got to source products, you've
got to select You've got to select
products, I should say. You've got to
source them in the right way and then
you've got to sell them in the right
manner." And people are like, "Okay,
there are three main key elements I need
to deal with." And then for each one of
these, I never give more than four, but
usually three ways in which they can
attack that. By continually focusing
them on just a few pieces of information
in their mind and making those
information's easy for them to put their
attention on, you will have more impact
in your messaging. Cognitive bias number
three, what we call the Barnum effect.
It's like he knows exactly who I am,
therefore he must know how to help me.
There's a secret structure of
communication that a lot of people just
aren't aware of that can make a massive
difference in influence and it's
properly structured
general statements
can have such a profound impact on
rapport, understanding,
and he gets me, which is what you want
to have every audience think when you
are communicating to them. And these are
things along the lines of when I speak
to an audience, I'll say, "Listen,
whether you find yourself just at the
beginning of the journey or if you have
some experience in this or even if
you've been doing this for a while, what
really matters at the end of the day is"
and then every single audience member
is going to say, "Okay, that relates to
me." I don't say, "Some people find
themselves at the beginning phase. Some
people find themselves in the middle,
and some people find themselves in the
end. Which one are you?" Uh but, that's
how everybody else does it. So, I
learned to speak the language of the
market while still talking to the
individual. And these are why we learn
to use conversational hypnosis as much
as possible. When you say, "You may
discover you have capabilities inside of
you that you aren't aware of yet." Now,
I didn't say which capabilities. I
didn't even say you will discover them.
I just gave you the idea that there are
things inside of you that are valuable
that you have not quite tapped into yet.
And 97% of all audiences, when you craft
the proper general statements that I've
just described to you, they will 100%
agree and nod and go along with what you
say. What we try to do is yes at the
best, but never no. So, yes at best, but
never no. So, you don't say, "You will
become more certain as you get more
experience." You say, "You may begin to
notice you become more certain and
operate in ways which are consistent
with those certainties when you act."
Not you will be more certain. You don't
say, "You are going to do this." You
say, "I'm not sure when you will do this
in a way that will allow you to feel
comfortable enough that you can
continue." So, see what I'm doing here?
I am artfully vague. And this is what we
call this in conversational psychology,
conversational hypnosis I should say. I
am artfully vague on the cold reads of
the market, but I understand
universalities of every single market.
And this is what they did when they
studied P.T. Barnum, who was one of the
greatest showmans of all time. They
discovered that there were certain
statements that almost everybody in any
market would agree to. And one of these
statements are, you have some weaknesses
inside you, but you can compensate for
them. So, most people believe this to be
true. I have these issues, but I'm able
to overcome them cuz I compensate in
these ways. So, we validate the
compensation and then we also enable
them to no longer be weak in those ways.
People just have such a desperate need
for other people to like and admire
them. So, whether they will admit it or
not, deep down inside, they have this
just drive for people to like who they
are and admire them. So, I only play in
markets where I like the people and I
love my audiences and I can admire the
efforts that they attempt and to solve
their problems. Unfortunately, a lot of
people don't go very far in this
business because they are cynical and
jaded against their audience. They will
call their audience lazy
and they will say that they don't take
action. And it will show up, usually
very subtly, in the communication. But I
admire an audience who's tried something
99 times and hasn't succeeded yet
because it shows me that they're
dedicated, that even in the face of
difficulty, they can find a way to move
on. I don't call that laziness. I call
that they haven't been shown the proper
path yet to help them move
forward. So, people believe that they
have a lot of unused dormant capacity
inside of them that hasn't been tapped
into yet. And I believe it, too. And
they believe that there are times when
they want to be around others and there
are times when they want to be alone.
And I know this is sounds like, duh,
obvious, but you should learn to
communicate to these basic universal
needs of the audience and they will nod
their head along with you, nod their
head along with you, nod their head
along with you, and they will like you
because they can tell you like them and
they will be more likely to respond with
the request that you make. Next bias,
the law
of triviality.
Even though we just spent 25 minutes in
the meeting talking about where to put
the ping pong tables in the break room,
it felt like it was a worthwhile
activity to discuss. We tend to major in
minor things. And this is a Jim Rohn
quote. And the reality is, and this is
especially pronounced in groups, this
gets psychopathic when you put a group
of people together. Now, I'll tell you
why individually first of all, is a
majority of things, at least 90% of all
the considerations when you're trying to
get a result, equal about 3%
of what is important. So, 90% we call
this noise, gives you 3%
of the results. And 10%, which is the
signal, accounts for the other 97%
of success. But we don't think that way.
We think in terms of equality. We think
if there's five elements that will
contribute to the success, then element
one is worth 20%, element two is worth
20%, element three is worth 20%, and so
on and so forth. But the reality is,
even in small numbers like this,
typically one of these elements will be
worth 90% and the other elements will be
worth something like 5%, 3%, 1%, 1%. So,
nothing is fair in life. Nothing is
organized neatly as such of the most
closed systems possible, like coin flips
and things like that. But the brain
doesn't understand and can't appreciate
nuance very easily, so you have to force
it and you have to train it. So, just
know whatever you're considering,
whatever you're thinking, it's probably
trivial. Now, this gets terrible when
you get into groups because people feel
most comfortable having discussions on
things where they share common grounds.
And so, most people, for example, if you
are trying to talk about spending a
budget of $50 million to allocate to new
software development, a majority of
people at the table have no reference
point to what $50 million
is. This is why they will quickly
approve, deny, or move past that agenda
item, but then they will spend forever
on the party for Christmas that's going
to happen at the end of the year and
what the theme should be. The theme for
the party at Christmas doesn't ever make
a difference really at the end of the
day, but how the budget is allocated
will. So, don't focus on common grounds
and bring agendas ahead of time that
have prioritized
what the major things are and limit it
to just one of those major things. Now,
when it comes to selling, the keyword
here is boundaries.
We only allow our clients and our
prospects to have conversations around
things that matter. And this is what I
say to them. When they start asking
these little questions that don't really
matter at the end of the day, I said,
"There's two types of questions that
somebody can ask. They can ask
nickel-and-dime questions, which really
don't matter at the end of the day
toward your success, or they can ask
hundred-dollar bill questions. These are
the things that will make or break you,
that will decide whether you should buy
or whether you should never buy. So,
when we're asking questions, while I
will attempt to answer every single one
of them, I'm going to prioritize by the
hundred-dollar bill questions first, the
ones that really matter at the end of
the day." And then all of a sudden, the
same audience who were asking little
silly things like how many times can I
log in? And does this come in blue as
well as red and pink and purple and
green? Those are the only things they
know how to ask ask right now. They
start asking real questions that will
make the difference in whether they
should purchase or not. The next
cognitive bias, bounded reality. She's
not the nicest looking car on the road,
but she gets me to where I want to go.
There was a groundbreaking psychological
study that determined that people are
one of two types. They're satisficers or
they're maximizers. And really most
people they're satisficers
if you will. They look at the thing that
is sufficient that will also satisfy
their needs. Some people, I hope you are
not one of them, are what are called
maximizers. Good enough is not good
enough. If it's not 100% perfectly the
best money for the deal, then they're
not going to feel happy with it even if
it made them so much money. I had a
client once that exited a company uh for
a billion dollars. And he had a $1
billion
wire transfer coming to him and he felt
depressed because he knew that he
screwed up. And if he would have just
done a couple key moves a little bit
earlier on in his business, he could
have exited for $3 billion instead. Uh
this is neurotic, okay? But this is how
people work. But most people in most
markets, this is really the breakdown,
is about 10% of a market is going to be
a maximizer and 90% is going to be a
satisficer. So, we prefer to settle for
good enough or sufficient versus
excellence. And the reason why is
because for the time involved and the
effort involved and the money involved,
it's just not a good use of any of these
principles. And so, when we are
designing offers, a big part of what
we're looking for is how do we not be
the best? How do we be the best at a
glance? How do we be the best with the
least amount of cognition required in
order to understand the value for the
time in? This is oftentimes where we go
to the move where we just say, "Listen,
it's just as good, but it's half the
time to the results." And so, we don't
have to be better than the competition,
we're just quicker than the competition.
We don't have to add additional things
which can create complication, we remove
the unnecessary things and people then
say, "Wow, that's really good." You just
got to get this through your mind.
People don't want objective best, they
want subjective best. Once you
understand that every prospect has
limited understanding, limited mental
processing, and limited time limits,
then you will design offers within those
areas of understanding, processing, and
time limitations. The next cognitive
bias, paradox of choice.
>> There's nothing good to watch on
Netflix. Here's something that's crazy
is the more choice that we have, the
more unhappy we are. So, more choices
equal less happiness. So, we have
Spotify, we have Apple Music, we have
YouTube Music, and yet we tend to be
more frustrated now because we think,
"Well, gee, if I would have listened to
this instead of that, then I could have
been happier. What music am I missing
out on that I would love to hear, but I
don't even know exist?" And every single
day there's more music that is published
than you could ever consume, so you
increase the FOMO and it gets crazy. And
nowhere is this more pronounced than
market segments. Um this is so difficult
for so many people that I coach to get
this through their head. If we delete
90% of the market, we will make more
money by just focusing on 10%. We do not
want to be all things to everyone. We
want to be a few things to a few people,
and we just want to be the best at those
few things to those few key people. This
is where the money is made. The easiest
way to get to the other 90% by the way
is to be excellent to the 10% and I'll
give you a case study on this. So, once
upon a time we had this product that was
called Launchpad and it was very similar
to ClickFunnels. So, ClickFunnels is
this builder that would teach you and
show you with clicks of a button how to
build certain funnels that you could
launch your products in. So, you know,
squeeze page here, thank you page here,
upsell them to this page, downsell to
that page, that kind of thing. Um and
ClickFunnels retailed for $297 a month
at the highest price point price tier.
Ours retailed for $1,000 a month.
ClickFunnels audience was essentially
everyone. All right? Our audience was
Amazon sellers and specifically Amazon
sellers who were successful already at
selling on Amazon. ClickFunnels would
have dozens, probably hundreds of funnel
uh campaigns and options that you could
configure and put together. We had five
funnels and they were basically the five
best funnels that we found to rank
products on Amazon's search engine.
ClickFunnels would have the ability to
have a lot of customization. You could
custom fonts, backgrounds, etc. Even you
could write all the copy you wanted to
write. Ours was you couldn't customize
anything except for a little bit of
copy. You couldn't change the font, you
couldn't change the background, you
couldn't change the size of the
container, and 85% of the copy was
already written for you because we can
write better copy than 99% of our
customers could write. And here's the
final thing and this is the most
important thing is is you could do
certain different tech here that you
could connect together or you could
optimize for you. The tech was open,
ours was closed tech. We hired we
hardwired certain technological
capabilities that would be impossible
for the end user to program on their own
and we bake them into the system simply
because we locked so many other things
down and we were able to sell 3.29
million dollars on a single webinar of a
software that 99.9% of the world never
seen or never heard. We gave less
choices to fewer people, they were just
the right few people and we did more for
those few people to help them become
more successful easier. The next bias,
cognitive
dissonance. I know I should eat healthy,
but I'm on vacation. Here's the crazy
thing about us as humans and I just
don't get it. It's hard for us to hold
two contradictive thoughts in our head
at the same time. It is painful to a
degree that doesn't make sense to too
many people where they say, I I don't
get it. If people like things faster,
then how come these Michelin star
restaurants do 4-hour dinners? I just
don't get it. Uh the reality is there's
paradoxes and then there's
contradictions. Uh so many things that
we think are paradoxes are are sorry,
things that are contradictions,
contradictions are actually paradoxes.
So a paradox is on the surface it it
appears as if it contradicts itself, but
on further examination, there's actually
some poetry to it. There's actually a
deeper meaning and reason why these two
things that seem at odds can actually
coexist. And here's the thing about
contradictions. Contradictions are not
terrible. The world is messy. If you
ever watch one of those uh based on a
true story kind of deals, you will find
that the true story that actually
happened in reality isn't clean as how
it appears on the big screen. That's
because we want our fiction to be neat
and clean because our non-fiction
reality is messy and hard to understand
and explain. So, when you get to the
idea that you don't have to solve every
contradiction and it's totally okay for
you to do things that don't make sense
when you put them side by side, but they
allow you to move forward, then you
don't have the friction anymore
And the chances are it's probably a
paradox anyway. Now, let me tell you how
this applies in business and marketing.
It's called congruence. Just make sure
that whatever you're doing to the end
user appears congruent. I'll give you
the example here. We like to do a lot of
beta launches. So, we launch a thing and
we say, "Listen, I don't know if this
will work or not, but we'd like to test
it out. We're going to take on a few key
people and try it out, see if it works.
But, hey, I got to warn you, it's going
to be bumpy. We haven't put the whole
thing together yet and we're making it
up as we go along, but so far the
results we've gotten are promising and I
wanted to get it in your hands as fast
as possible." Now, when I teach this to
clients, they say, "Okay, got it, Jason.
I'm going to go do a beta launch." And
then they put together the most
professional-looking
pages and designs you've ever seen. And
I'm like, "You can either be
professional or you can be in beta, but
you can't be both." And even if
audiences don't understand this
consciously, unconsciously, something
feels off. So, just sanity check your
congruence from start to finish when
you're launching your business and
marketing campaigns and your positions
because if two things are at odds with
each other and they appear
contradictive, your audience will feel
uncomfortable with them. The next bias,
affect heuristic.
I just walked across hot coals. Now, I
can do anything. The craziness about
this is our brain is so powerful. It has
It has something that it can do that no
other animal can do, which is be
logical, but we're almost never logical
anyway. Even when we feel like we're
logical, notice the word feel. We
overvalue emotions so heavily that we
allow them to influence
the decisions we make to a unbelievably
crazy degree. So, the whole idea of like
the gut feeling, people will only
remember when their gut was right, they
will value that, and then they will
think they should always act according
to their gut feeling. But, what they
don't realize is that just because it
feels good and feels right doesn't make
it right. And if it feels uncomfortable,
that in and of itself isn't sufficient
to make it feel wrong because most of
the areas of growth live in what are
uncomfortable habitats initially. Now,
what we want to do when we sell is we
want to minimize the feeling of
discomfort, so we want to do everything
that we can to bring that down, and we
also want to maximize the types of
emotions that people base decisions
around. So, if you ask somebody some ask
them this question sometime, this is an
NLP question. Think of a time you made a
really good decision, and then you get
the person to think, and then you can
say, "How do you know it was a good
decision?" And they'll say, "Well," and
then they'll give you a bunch of content
that doesn't really matter. But, you
say, "No, no. Where does the good
decision first show up as a feeling in
your body?" "Oh, well, it starts right
here." And they'll tell you if you ask
them, right? And how do you know versus
a bad decision? Where is the feeling
different when it's a bad decision
versus when it's a good decision? How
did you know it was a good decision
looking back on it? And then when you
made a bad decision, how did you know it
was a bad decision only when you look
back on it later? Like, we are giving
what's called the decision-making
criteria.
We are eliciting it to know how this
person feels like something is good or
bad. It is not logical, but it is the
code in which they make their decisions.
And this is so, so powerful because
you'll very quickly realize that people,
when they feel negative emotions, they
start to overvalue
and oversubscribe
and overweight negative emotions. And
they undervalue
the logical positive rewards. They will
literally think a dollar to risk is $10,
and they will think the reward for $10
is $2. And you will sit there scratching
your head thinking, "Well, I don't get
it. This is the best deal in the world."
And yet they're still not buying. So, we
have to help people remove the emotional
baggage that gets in the way of the
decisions that they should make so they
can properly ascertain and understand
value.